Mushrooms and cancer survival?
Check out this video to
find out the results
of randomized controlled trials
of mushroom consumption
in cancer patients.
"Mushrooms for Prostate Cancer
and Cancer Survival"
Can mushrooms be medicinal?
Mushroom-based products
make up a sizable chunk of the
$50 billion supplement market.
This profitable trade provides a powerful
incentive for companies to test
the credulity of their customers, and
sadly, unsupported assertions
have come to define the
medical mushroom business.
For example, companies that market herbal
medicines exploit references to studies
on mice to promote their
mushroom capsules
for treating all kinds of ailments,
but if you haven't noticed,
we're not mice.
I mean, it wouldn't be surprising if
mushrooms had some potent properties.
After all, fungi are where
we got a bunch of drugs,
not the least of which, penicillin.
And also a cholesterol-lowering
drug, lovastatin,
and the powerful immunosuppressant
drug, cyclosporin.
Still don't think a little mushroom
can have pharmacological effects?
Don't forget they can produce some
of our most powerful poisons.
Some kind of look the part, like
the toxic Carolina false morel,
all toadstooly and such, but others
have more of an angelic look,
indeed literally called the
Destroying Angel—that's its name—
and as little as a teaspoon can
cause a painful, lingering death.
So anyway, we should have respect
for the pharmacological potential
of mushrooms, but what can
they do that's good for us?
Well, consuming shiitake mushrooms
daily improves human immunity.
Giving people just one or two
dried shiitake mushrooms a day—
about the weight equivalent of five
to ten fresh ones—for four weeks
resulted in an increase in proliferation
of gamma-delta T lymphocytes
and doubled the proliferation
of natural killer cells.
Gamma-delta cells act as a first
line of immunological defense,
and even better,
natural killer cells kill cancer,
and the shiitake did all this while
lowering markers of systemic inflammation.
Oyster mushroom extracts don't seem
to work as well, but what we care about
is if mushrooms can actually
affect cancer outcomes.
Shiitakes haven't been tried yet,
but reishi mushrooms have,
after being used as a cancer treatment
throughout Asia for centuries.
Reishi mushroom for cancer treatment:
what does the science say?
A meta-analysis of five randomized
controlled trials showed that patients
who had been given reishi mushroom
supplements along with chemo and
radiation were more likely to
respond positively compared
to just chemo and radiation alone.
Now although adding a reishi mushroom
extract improved tumor response rates,
the data failed to demonstrate
a significant effect on tumor shrinkage
when the mushrooms were used alone.
So they aren't recommended
as a single treatment,
but rather an adjunct treatment
for patients with advanced cancer.
Now response rate just
means the tumor shrinks.
What we care about is whether
or not it actually improves
survival or quality of life. And
we don't have convincing data
suggesting reishi mushroom
products improve survival.
But those randomized to
reishi were found to have
a relatively better quality of life, so
that's a win as far as I'm concerned.
What about other mushrooms?
Although whole shiitake mushrooms
haven't been tested yet,
there's a compound that's extracted
from shiitakes called lentinan,
which is said to have
completely inhibited the growth
of a certain kind of sarcoma in mice.
But in actuality it only worked
in one single strain of mice
and failed in nine others.
So are we more like the 90% of
mouse strains in which it didn't work?
We need human trials,
and we finally got them.
There are data on nearly 10,000
cancer patients who have been treated
with the shiitake mushroom extract
injected right into their veins.
What did the researchers find?
We'll find out next.
A regular intake of mushrooms is said to
make us healthier, fitter, and happier,
and help us live longer. But what
is the evidence for all of that?
Mushrooms are widely cited for their
medicinal qualities, yet very few
rigorous human intervention
studies have been done.
There is a compound called lentinan,
extracted from shiitake mushrooms.
To get about an ounce you have to
distill around 400 pounds of shiitakes.
That's like 2,000 cups of mushrooms.
But then you can inject the compound into
cancer patients and see what happens.
The pooled response from a dozen
small clinical trials found that
the objective response rate
was significantly improved
when lentinan was added to
chemotherapy regimens for lung cancer.
"Objective response rate"
means like tumor shrinkage,
but what we really care about
is survival and quality of life.
Does it actually make cancer patients
live any longer or any better?
Well, those in the lentinan group
suffered less chemo-related toxicity
to their gut and bone marrow,
so that alone might be
reason enough to use it.
But what about improving survival?
I was excited to see that lentinan
evidently could
significantly improve survival rates
for a type of leukemia. And here it is.
Adding lentinan increased average
survival and reduced cachexia—
which is like cancer-associated muscle
wasting—and improved cage-side health.
Wait, what? How...
Damn it.
This was improved survival
for brown Norwegian rats.
So that so-called clinical benefit
only applies if you're a veterinarian.
A compilation of 17 actual human
clinical studies did find improvements
in one-year survival in
advanced cancer patients,
but no significant difference in the
likelihood of living out to two years.
Even the compilations of studies
that purport that lentinan offers a
significant advantage in terms of survival
are talking about statistical significance.
It's hard to tell these
survival curves apart.
Lentinan improved survival
by an average of 25 days.
Now, 25 days is 25 days, but we should
evaluate claims made by companies
about the miraculous properties of
medicinal mushrooms very critically.
Lentinan has to be
injected intravenously.
What about mushroom extract
supplements you can just take yourself?
Shiitake mushroom extract is available
through the Internet for the treatment
of prostate cancer for
approximately $300 a month,
so it's got to be good, right?
Men who regularly eat mushrooms
do seem to be at lower risk
for getting prostate cancer,
and not apparently just because
they eat less meat or more fruits
and vegetables in general. So why not
give a shiitake mushroom extract a try?
Because it doesn't work—ineffective in
the treatment of clinical prostate cancer.
The results demonstrate that
complementary and alternative
medicine claims can actually be
put to the test. What a concept!
Maybe it should be mandatory before
patients spend large sums of money
on unproven treatments, or in
this case, a disproven treatment.
What about God's mushroom, also
known as the Mushroom of Life
or reishi mushrooms?
Conclusions: no significant
anticancer effects were found,
not even a single partial response.
Maybe we're overthinking it?
Plain white button mushroom
extracts can kill off prostate
cancer cells,
at least in a petri dish,
but so could the fancy God's mushroom,
but that didn't end up working in people.
You don't know if plain white
button mushrooms work or not
until you put it to the test.
What I like about this study is that
the researchers didn't use
a proprietary extract. They just
used regular whole mushrooms,
dried and powdered—
the equivalent of a half cup
to a cup and a half of fresh white
button mushrooms a day—
in other words, a totally doable amount.
They gave them to men
with biochemically recurrent
prostate cancer.
What that means is the men had already
gotten a prostatectomy or radiation
in an attempt to cut or burn out all the
cancer, but now it's back and growing,
as evidenced by a rise in PSA levels, an
indicator of prostate cancer progression.
Of the 26 patients who got
the button mushroom powder,
four appeared to respond,
meaning they got a drop
in PSA levels by more than
50% after starting the 'shrooms.
Here's where the four responders
started out in the months leading up
to starting the mushrooms.
Patient 2 was my favorite.
He had an exponential increase
in PSA levels for a year.
Then he started some
plain white mushrooms,
and boom, his PSA level drop
down to zero and stays down.
Similar type responses
with patient 1.
Patient 4 had a partial response,
before his cancer took off again,
and Patient 3 appeared to have
a delayed partial response.
Now in the majority of cases,
the PSA levels continued to rise,
not dipping at all.
But even if there is only a 1 in 18
chance you'll be like these two
with a prolonged complete
response that continues to date,
we're not talking about weighing the
risks of some toxic chemotherapy
for the small chance of benefit; just
eating some inexpensive, easy, tasty,
plain white mushrooms every day.
Yes, the study didn't
have a control group,
so it may have just
been coincidence,
but post-prostatectomy patients
with rising PSAs are almost always
indicators of cancer progression.
And, hey, what's the downside?
I mean these two patients, their
PSA levels became undetectable,
suggesting that the cancer
disappeared altogether.
They'd already gone through surgery,
gotten their primary tumor removed
along with their entire prostate,
already went through radiation to try
to clean up any cancer that remained,
and yet the cancer appeared
to be surging back
until, that is, they started
a little plain mushroom powder.